Guide to the Stanford Humanities Lab Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford Humanities Lab records
circa 1999-2009
SC1061
Lowood, Henry
Schnapp, Jeffrey T. (Jeffrey Thompson), 1954-
Shanks, Michael.
Stanford Humanities Lab.
11161.6 megabyte(s)
The materials consist of administrative records, subject files, conference materials, and email documenting the functions and projects of the Stanford Humanities Lab.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
Open for research.
Biographical/Historical note
Founded by Jeffrey Schnapp (Comparative Literature) in 1999, the Stanford Humanities Lab (SHL) enabled scholars in the humanities to undertake mid- to large-scale team-based research projects. By supporting innovative research, SHL sought to expand the scope and scale of humanitas, supplementing traditional humanities training with "hands-on" experiences in a true laboratory setting. In 2003, Henry Lowood (Curator for History of Science & Technology Collections; Film & Media Collections) became co-director of the lab. Schanpp and Lowood were later joined by Michael Shanks (Archaeology), who directed lab as a team until 2009 when it evolved into separate projects. The Stanford Humanities Lab was a Center for Transdiciplinary/Post-Disciplinary Study. With new developments in areas such as biotech, digital culture, global society, SHL believed that some crucial questions — about what it is to be human, about experience in a connected world, about the boundaries of culture and nature — transcend the old divisions between the arts, sciences and humanities, between the academy, industry and the cultural sphere.
SHL engaged in experimental projects with a "laboratory" ethos — collaborative, co-creative, team-based — involving a triangulation of arts practice, commentary/critique, and outreach, merging research, pedagogy, publication and practice. They didn't just comment and discuss, they built: new media, interactive archives, predictive models of social change, new courses, collaborative research workshops, art exhibitions.
The SHL agenda encompassed: • animating archives - regenerating, bringing to life, and fostering new modes of interaction with the storehouses of human, cultural, artistic, scientific achievement - our focus is on the question of the relationship of the human past to efforts at conservation and preservation
• building bigger pictures - putting specialized in-depth research into the context of big human questions; questions, for example, of rapid social change and innovation, the ethical implications of information technology, the character of distributed digital communities, the politics of digital citizenship, the past, present, and future of intellectual property • enabling co-creative collaboration - developing successful models of teamwork, learner-centered models of training (thinking through doing), and collaborative authoring tools and processes • building bridges - establishing innovative partnerships between industry, museums, foundations, and high-level university-based research
Projects The Lab offered the opportunity for scholars in the humanities to undertake the sort of mid- to large-scale team-based research projects that have traditionally been the domain of the natural and social sciences. Humanities disciplines have generally received far more modest research funding than the sciences, thus discouraging resource-intensive scholarship as well as collaborative or team-based work. These limitations have resulted in research findings—usually in print form—that are produced and consumed by individual scholars working in isolation, and shared with students exclusively in the classroom setting.
SHL sought to change that. Whereas institutional pressures have fostered a narrowing of research agendas, SHL promoted a model of the humanities that is flexible and cross-disciplinary at its core and at the same time rooted in the disciplinary traditions of the humanities. By providing financial support for innovative humanities research with results that assume technologically inflected forms, SHL attempted:
• to expand the scope and scale of humanitas
• to supplement traditional humanities training with "hands-on" experiences in a true laboratory setting
• to add an outreach dimension to traditional disciplinary endeavors
After an initial pilot year, projects were typically funded for five to seven years, during which SHL administrative and technical staff were involved in helping to shepherd the work to successful completion. Administrative staff helped with working methodology, such pragmatic details as helping to build partnerships with museums and other public institutions, fundraising, and presenting work to the campus and wider community.
Technical staff helped researchers imagine outputs and results beyond the limits of their technology skills. They assisted in locating digital artist collaborators, programmers, video producers, animators, and others to help realize researchers' ideas. And they instructed research teams not only on how to supervise the creation of technology-driven outputs but also on how to do hands-on programming, film production, animation, etc. of their own.
Teaching SHL projects were rooted in the disciplinary traditions of the Humanities, but they involve students from a wide array of Humanities and non-Humanities disciplines. Many SHL projects involved a recurring course or seminar component that allows team members to introduce, develop, and test their research results within the classroom. SHL was a research center, but teaching is central to its mission. The SHL aim was to lead a revolution in the way knowledge is produced and presented in the Humanities and, in so doing, to provide a compelling new model for Humanities education that:
• enhances and deepens traditional classroom teaching
• integrates the latest technologies and tools into Humanities research and vice versa
• breeds a new kind of Humanities-savvy "techie" and a new kind of tech-savvy "fuzzy"
To this end, SHL projects involved a new hands-on, laboratory-based model of undergraduate and graduate training, informed by the media and information revolutions of the present. Students learned not only by studying knowledge in the traditional manner, but also by producing knowledge: by being assigned responsibility for the realization of a piece of research within a larger research mosaic, overseen by an experienced senior researcher.
Scope and Contents
The materials consist of administrative records, subject files, conference materials, and email documenting the functions and projects of the Stanford Humanities Lab.
Arrangement note
The materials are arranged in two series: Series 1. Computer Files; Series 2. Paper files.
Access Terms
Digital humanities centers.; Humanities; Humanities--Data processing.; Humanities--Study and teaching (Higher).; Humanities--Study and teaching--California --Stanford.
Collection Contents
- Computer Files, Series 1; 11 gigabyte(s) (17,780 files in 1058 directories)
  - How They Got Game - SHL project, 6.41 gigabyte(s)
  - HPS - SHL project, 690 megabyte(s)
  - Eudora email, 2003; Lowood, Henry; 385 megabyte(s)
    - attach
    - Game Project.fol
    - archive.mbx
    - archive.toc
  - Thunderbird email, 2011; Lowood, Henry; 42.4 megabyte(s)
    - htgg_20110818-1347
      - messages
      - index.html
    - shl_20110818-1341
      - messages
      - index.html
    - shl_20110818-1344
      - messages
      - index.html
  - Shl, 3.49 gigabyte(s)
- Paper Files, Series 2
  - SHL (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - AWSM (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Digital humanities (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - How they got game (SHL) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - HPS simulations--AFOSR grant (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Electronic Arts (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Why game studies now? (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Digital person reader (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Game colelction--National Vanguard, Resistance games (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Springer book (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Machinima (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Wargame book (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - HASTAC (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - HASTAC, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Exhibit (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Exhibit planning--How they got game (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Storytelling--Virtual World Conference, Stanford, 2004 Feb (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - YBCA (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Bits of culture (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - History of computer game characters, 2003 Apr (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Henrik Bennetsen (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Digital humanities (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Preserving Creative America (Library of Congress) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Game archive project, Kyoto (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Hastac (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Xfive (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Center for digital imaging and sound (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Gamespot (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - How they got game book (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Military simulation archives (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Panel on cultural legacy of video games, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - E3, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Game Developers Conference--IGDA, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Future of content, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Future of content, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Online gaming, 2004 Feb (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Wizards of OS3, Berlin, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Arizona, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Digital vision, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Gaming to learn workshop, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - DIGRA, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Serious Games, DC, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - 030303--Collective play (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - HSS, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - History of computer game design (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - STS 145: History of Computer Game Design, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 46-47)
  - STS 145: History of Computer Game Design, 2001-2005 (Box 2, Folder 1-8)